Hello, AP US students.  Here's
the first period in two minutes.  The
first period begins in 1491 with the
study of Native
American cultures before European contact.
The natives developed
unique cultures based on climate and
geography.  In Central and South America,
the Aztecs and the Mayans depended on the
cultivation of corn.  These tribes were
large and complex, with
intricate trade networks,
sophisticated calendars, and irrigation systems.  In
North America, the tribes were
mostly small and semi-nomadic
.  The indigenous peoples of the Great
Plains hunted buffalo and lived in
tipis, while those near the
Great Lakes lived in
permanent dwellings such as longhouses and
developed agriculture.  But everything
changed in 1492 when Christopher
Columbus arrived in the Americas.  This
brings us to one of the most
important concepts of the first period: the
Columbian Exchange.  It refers to the
exchange of plants, animals, ideas
, people, and diseases between the
Old and New Worlds.
European nations gained wealth by exploiting
these new resources and experienced a
population boom thanks to new
food sources.  And although the
natives obtained horses, which
helped in hunting, their populations
were devastated by new
diseases such as smallpox.
Spanish colonization also led
to the rise of the conquistadors who
sought gold, God, and glory.
CollegeBoard's favorite example is Hernán
Cortés, who brutally conquered
the Aztecs.  The conquerors
also established the
encomienda system to enslave
native populations and force them to
convert to Catholicism.  This
also led to the establishment of the
caste system, a
racial hierarchy with Spaniards at the top,
mestizos and mulattos in the middle, and
natives and enslaved Africans at the
base.  But many questioned the
harsh treatment of the natives, which led to the
Valladolid debates.  In these debates
, the Catholic priest Bartolomé de
las Casas supported the conversion of the
natives, but opposed the brutality
of the encomienda system.  But Juan
Ginés de Sepúlveda argued that the
natives were barbarians and that the
Spaniards had the right to
enslave them.  In the end, these debates
led to the decline of the
encomienda system, but it was replaced by the
asiento system, which enslaved
Africans.  Thanks for watching, and if
you want more help with APUSH such as
study guides, timelines, and
summary videos, be sure to
check out the Ultimate Revision Package
.